<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<GameData>
	<EnglishText>
		<!--New-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BARBARIAN_CLANS_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Barbarian Clans Mode</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BARBARIAN_CLANS_CHAPTER_WELCOME_TITLE">
			<Text>Welcome</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_BARBARIAN_CLANS_CHAPTER_WELCOME_PARA_1">
			<Text>This game mode replaces standard Barbarian Tribes with a diverse set of Clans, each with its own terrain and combat preferences.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGEGROUP_CLANS_NAME">
			<Text>Barbarian Clans</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- Game Mode Concept -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Barbarian Clans</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_WELCOME_TITLE">
			<Text>Welcome</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_WELCOME_PARA_1">
			<Text>In game setup, players can turn on the Barbarian Clans game mode, introducing greater diversity to Barbarians and new player interactions with them.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_TYPES_TITLE">
			<Text>Types of Clans</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_TYPES_PARA_1">
			<Text>Replacing the melee, cavalry, and naval tribes in standard rules, this mode includes seven types of Barbarian clans. Each clan type has its own preferred range of units to field and requires a different set of map conditions in order to appear.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_TYPES_PARA_2">
			<Text>Melee tribes are represented by Woodland clans that favor ranged units, Hills clans that favor melee and anti-cavalry units, and a Flatland clan with a balanced approach.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_TYPES_PARA_3">
			<Text>Cavalry tribes are represented by Rover clans that favor a diversity of mounted units, Chariot clans that favor vehicles as well as mounted units, and Jungle clans that favor a mixture of cavalry and foot soldiers.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_TYPES_PARA_4">
			<Text>Naval tribes are represented by the Seafaring clan with a balanced approach to naval units.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_UNITS_TITLE">
			<Text>Clans and Unique Units</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_UNITS_PARA_1">
			<Text>In addition to their normal units, clans also have the ability to field Unique Units from around the world.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_UNITS_PARA_2">
			<Text>In any game with Clans Mode active, the Unique Units associated with civilizations not present in that game are made available for Barbarian clans to claim and use. Clans will periodically claim an available unique unit from among those that match its playstyle and are close in power to the clan's current best unit. Once any clan claims a Unique Unit, it will have exclusive access to it while the clan exists. If the clan is destroyed, the claim is cleared and another clan could claim the same unit on a subsequent turn.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_CITYCONVERSION_TITLE">
			<Text>Clan Conversions to City-States</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_CITYCONVERSION_PARA_1">
			<Text>In this mode, clans that successfully remain in play long enough can convert into City-States.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_CITYCONVERSION_PARA_2">
			<Text>Every clan makes progress towards conversion each turn based on the [ICON_FOOD] Food yield of unowned tiles around their Outpost. Beneficial player activies such as hiring or bribing the clan can speed up their progress, while violent activities like raiding and inciting can slow it down. When the clan has made enough progress, they become a candidate to convert on that or any subsequent turn.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_CITYCONVERSION_PARA_3">
			<Text>When a Barbarian Clan converts into a City-State, their Outpost is immediately replaced by the new city under its new name, and all existing clan units become units of the new City-State. The City-State will also be immediately introduced to any civilizations that had discovered the clan.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_CITYCONVERSION_PARA_4">
			<Text>Based on the game's settings, only a certain number of clan conversions can occur. Once all possible conversions have occurred, all current and future clans will remain Barbarians for the duration of the game.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_UNITCOMMANDS_TITLE">
			<Text>Raiding and Dispersing Clans</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_UNITCOMMANDS_PARA_1">
			<Text>Combat units that enter a Barbarian Outpost do not automatically destroy it. Instead, they can choose from two new unit commands to deal with the clan: Raid and Disperse.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_UNITCOMMANDS_PARA_2">
			<Text>Raiding an Outpost rewards [ICON_GOLD] Gold to the player and reduces the clan's progress towards City-State conversion, but does not destroy the Outpost. When a clan is raided, it gains immunity to raids for a short duration. Raided clans will also spawn a defender unit in reprisal the same turn they are raided, ejecting any foreign unit in their Outpost in the process.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_UNITCOMMANDS_PARA_3">
			<Text>Dispersing an Outpost will destroy the clan completely and earn a substantial amount of Experience Points for the dispersing unit.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_PLAYEROPS_TITLE">
			<Text>Advanced Interactions with Clans</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_PLAYEROPS_PARA_1">
			<Text>Besides the options for combat with clan units and Outposts, players can take peaceful or diplomatic actions with clans. These include Hiring, Bribing, Inciting, and Ransoming units from the clan. To initiate one of these interactions, click on the map banner over the Outpost. If the Outpost's location is not revealed to you, these interactions will be unavailable as well.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_PLAYEROPS_PARA_2">
			<Text>HIRING a clan: spend [ICON_GOLD] Gold to purchase a military unit from the clan. The unit provided will be the best the clan can currently train -- it could even be a Unique Unit!  Unlike levying a City-State, hired units are permanently under your control. They appear the same turn on a plot near to your closest city. Clans that are hired cannot be hired again for a short duration. Hiring a clan increases their City-State conversion progress.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_PLAYEROPS_PARA_3">
			<Text>BRIBING a clan: spend [ICON_GOLD] Gold to expel clan units from your territory and prevent them from targeting your cities for a set number of turns. Bribe costs start low but scale up the more cities you have. Clans that are bribed cannot be bribed again by the same player until the bribe expires, but they can be bribed by more than one player at a time. Bribing a clan increases their City-State conversion progress.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_PLAYEROPS_PARA_4">
			<Text>INCITING a clan: spend [ICON_GOLD] Gold to encourage the clan to raid and attack the cities of another civilization. You and the clan must share knowledge of at least one other civilization or City-State to be able to incite them. Incite costs are high, but the incitement has no expiration. However, clans can only be incited against one civilization at a time. Inciting a clan reduces its progress towards City-State conversion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_PLAYEROPS_PARA_5">
			<Text>RANSOMING a unit from a clan: if a clan has captured one of your civilian units, you can spend [ICON_GOLD] Gold to recover it. The cost to ransom a unit is always slightly less than the cost to purchase it new in one of your cities. Ransomed units appear the same turn at your closest City Center. Clans that ransom units lose progress towards City-State conversion.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_PLAYEROPS_PARA_6">
			<Text>Bribing a clan and ransoming a unit from them are exclusive: while a clan has one of your units held hostage, they will not listen to your bribe offers! You must recapture or ransom all units from a clan before you can bribe them again.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_TITLE">
			<Text>History</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The word "barbarian" comes from Greek (with a related term, "barbara", in Sanskrit), where it refers to people who could not speak the language (and sounded like they were saying "bar bar bar"). So what "barbarians" had in common was not being of a different race or ethnicity, but being on the outside of what people thought of as the cultural center. Whether we are talking about the Gauls (barbarians to the Greeks), or the Sakas ("mleccha" to the ancient Indians), or the Xiongnu (one of the "Five Hu," or Five Barbarians who plagued Han Dynasty China), empires and states had a way of determining who was "in," and who was "out."</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But despite the best propaganda efforts of empires, historical barbarians were not the savages that their settled rivals thought them to be. They were neither backwards people who had yet to progress to settled life, nor were they people that existed uncontacted by nation-states. Rather, non-state peoples existed in tandem with nations. As the geographer James C. Scott writes, early states made great efforts to control (often coercively) populations into living in close-clustered and unhealthy communities where their surplus production could be controlled and appropriated. Barbarian life, on the other hand, offered an option for freedom, and barbarian groups became both a source of raiders and pirates that preyed on the states, but also a means through which states could extend trade and diplomatic networks across territory that they did not have to control directly. Barbarian and civilized – the two are interdependent.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Clan Type: Melee Open-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_MELEE_OPEN_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Flatland clan is a type of Clan present when Barbarian Clans mode is active.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_MELEE_OPEN_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Flatland clans prefer to place their Outposts in open terrain away from woods and hills. They prefer a balance of melee units for attack and ranged units for defense.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_MELEE_OPEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_TITLE">
			<Text>History</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_MELEE_OPEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Flatland peoples live in the great plains and warm savannahs of the world. They travel on foot (otherwise they’d be under the banner of the Rover or Chariot Clan), but like those people, flatland peoples are often pastoralists. This term refers to people who live by and with herd animals: sheep, goats, cattle, etc. – on soil unsuited to farming, pastoralists move across the landscape and thus often escape (or seek to escape) capture by cities and states. Of these, East African groups: Maasai, Turkana, Nuer, and others are some of the most famous – people who live most of their lives off of their cattle’s blood, milk, and meat. For many of these groups, cattle become a vital part of their lives – livestock indicate a person’s status, a well-taken care of cow becomes a point of pride and obsession, and animals are exchanged at weddings. But these are not nomads. The Nuer of South Sudan, for instance, lived in the past century in settled communities. These were, according to anthropologist E. Evans-Pritchard, largely classless and egalitarian, but with a particular "leopard-skin chief" whose sole purpose is to mediate disputes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_MELEE_OPEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>A lack of internal hierarchy, however, does not mean pacifism: many flatland groups supplemented their livelihoods with a little bit of raiding – or with tribute money collected from threats of raids. The Nuer and Dinka held and continue to hold a bitter rivalry. And the Maasai of Kenya were and are famous for their weapons, especially their "ol alem" sword-spears. Although horseless, Maasai warriors are famous for their speed on foot – as Kenya’s consistent success in setting marathon records attests!</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Clan Type: Melee Woodland-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_MELEE_FOREST_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Woodland clan is a type of Clan present when Barbarian Clans mode is active.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_MELEE_FOREST_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Woodland clans prefer to place their Outposts in or adjacent to woods and rainforests. They prefer greater numbers of ranged units than melee units and use them for both attack and defense.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_MELEE_FOREST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_TITLE">
			<Text>History</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_MELEE_FOREST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>For those seeking an independent life, free from cities, states and kings and all the injustices that come with them, forests provide ideal cover. They are unsuitable to the kinds of intensive grain agriculture that urbanized states depend on, and they provide plenty of places to hide from slaving runs from autocratic states or to stage raids. Here, "forest clans" refer to groups such as the Tungus in the Siberian taiga, smaller indigenous groups in North America such as the Shawnee, Haudenosaunee (Iroquois), or Powhatan, or the various indigenous groups of the rain forest.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_MELEE_FOREST_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Life in temperate forests involves moving between scattered hunting camps in the winter (when hunting deer in the forest is more viable) to summer gatherings. In the tropics, some groups might practice "swidden agriculture" – cutting and burning sections of the jungle in a rotating pattern that, over time, was sustainable for village life. Other groups, such as the Achuar of the Amazon, did not directly cultivate, but seeded particular areas of the forest with crops that would, eventually, become a kind of shadow agriculture. While today many of these groups face increased pressure from logging or mining companies, historically forest peoples traded with urban zones, especially in goods such as furs, medicines, or spices.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Clan Type: Melee Hills-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_MELEE_HILLS_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Hills clan is a type of Clan present when Barbarian Clans mode is active.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_MELEE_HILLS_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Hills clans prefer to place their Outposts on open terrain with hills. They strongly prefer melee units, even to the point of excluding ranged units completely.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_MELEE_HILLS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_TITLE">
			<Text>History</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_MELEE_HILLS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the spur of the Himalayas lying within present-day Burma, Laos and neighboring countries, local kingdoms often divided people into two categories – hill and valley. Valley people – Shan, Thai, Burmese, or Lao – grew rice, were Buddhist, and were subject to the rule of the king. But highland people – the Akha, Hmong, Mien, or Kachin – were animist, grew root crops, and existed under their own, largely egalitarian, law. These divisions marked political, religious, and economic worlds, but they were also porous. Lowlanders fleeing a repressive king might flee to the hills, while highlanders attracted by urban life might descend.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_MELEE_HILLS_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>At times, these relationships were peaceful, and these groups traded openly – salt and silver from the hills; manufactured goods from the lowlands. But this peace was fragile. Lowland states would raid highland groups (something which the fact that the Laotian word for highland people - kha - was a synonym for "slave" attests), or highlanders might decide they didn’t want to trade for lowland goods and go on raids to get what they wanted. Some of these highland groups cultivated a fearsome reputation. The Wa of Burma, for instance, kept the heads of their enemies posted outside of their villages, not only showing the prowess of Wa warriors, but also enlisting – so the story went – the spirits of the dead in guarding the village. Over time, these highland groups became political actors in their own right, as they were courted by, at different times, British (in the colonial period) and American (in the Cold War) forces in attempts to find allies against lowland states in their own quests for domination.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Clan Type: Cavalry Open-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_CAVALRY_OPEN_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Rover clan is a type of Clan present when Barbarian Clans mode is active.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_CAVALRY_OPEN_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Rover clans require a nearby [ICON_RESOURCE_HORSES] Horses resource and prefer to place their Outposts in open terrain away from woods. They prefer as many mounted units as possible, using both light and heavy cavalry for attack and defense.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_CAVALRY_OPEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_TITLE">
			<Text>History</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_CAVALRY_OPEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>When horses arrived on the Great Plains of North America, they transformed everything. The plains previously were difficult places in which to live – they were abundant in bison, but hunting the great herds meant trapping them in places where they could be chased off of cliffs or ambushed. But a hunter on horseback could pursue bison herds at their own pace, for miles. Over a century, a whole way of life emerged around the horse and the mounted warrior, leading to the legacies of the great indigenous tribes of the plains: the Lakota (and other "Sioux" groups), the Apsáalooke (Crow), the Tsitsistas (Cheyenne), and others.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_CAVALRY_OPEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Similarly, but over a longer period of time, on the steppes of Asia, horse-bound nomadic pastoralists developed new technologies – most significantly the composite bow, which can be fired with the strength of a longbow, but is smaller and suitable for cavalry – that allowed them to stage devastating raids into settled lands. In addition to the Mongolians and Scythians, groups such as the Xiongnu, the Saka, the Kazakhs, and various Turkic-speaking peoples created vast, highly mobile armies that posed an existential threat to (complacent) cities. Nearly every agricultural state bordering the steppe has legends of conflicts (and defeats from) these groups: the Great Wall was built to counter Xiongnu raids, Korean history talks about struggles with the Jurchen, and the Romans had their Hunnic threat. All this came from the deep bond between horse and human, a link that we today have largely lost, as we turn towards combustion engines, treads and tires.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Clan Type: Cavalry Jungle-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_CAVALRY_JUNGLE_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Jungle clan is a type of Clan present when Barbarian Clans mode is active.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_CAVALRY_JUNGLE_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Jungle clans require a nearby [ICON_RESOURCE_IVORY] Ivory resource and prefer to place their Outposts inside rainforests. They prefer a mixture of light and heavy cavalry units supported by foot and ranged units.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_CAVALRY_JUNGLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_TITLE">
			<Text>History</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_CAVALRY_JUNGLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Rainforests provide another place of refuge for those seeking to escape – or a base from which raiders can operate. The Amazon, the Central African rainforest, and in the forests of Southeast Asia (especially Borneo/Kalimantan), are all home to vastly diverse populations of people living in what can be an unforgiving environment. Some of these cultivated a fearsome reputation as well as a skill in managing the alliances and rivalries of the time – the Tamoio people of the Amazon, for instance, organized themselves into a loose confederacy and fought against Portuguese colonial powers (selectively allying themselves with other European powers), just as groups like the Karen of highland Burma allied with the British against the lowland Burmese. Some of these groups increased their reputation by displaying the heads of their enemies – the Bugkalot of the Philippines and Dayaks of Indonesia both took heads, and the famous "shrunken heads" of the Amazon were actually de-boned and mummified heads made by Achuar and other groups.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_CAVALRY_JUNGLE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>When we think of the military capability of rainforest groups, we might think of blowguns (Amazon), crossbows (Southeast Asia), and spears (everywhere), and lightly-armored soldiers on foot. But they also had tanks: elephants. Elephants’ soft feet make little damage to the forest floor, they are able to move through thick cover relatively easily, and their height allows them to forge swollen jungle streams. In 20th century warfare, the Kachin of Burma used (and use) elephants to great effect against the Burmese army. While the treads and tires of Burmese army vehicles were bogged down in muddy ground, Kachin elephants could pass in relative silence, enabling them to outflank and outmaneuver their supposedly better-armed opponents.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Clan Type: Cavalry Chariot-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_CAVALRY_CHARIOT_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Chariot clan is a type of Clan present when Barbarian Clans mode is active.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_CAVALRY_CHARIOT_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Chariot clans require a nearby [ICON_RESOURCE_HORSES] Horses resource and prefer to place their Outposts in the desert. They prefer mounted vehicles and light cavalry in all roles, rarely using ranged units at all.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_CAVALRY_CHARIOT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_TITLE">
			<Text>History</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_CAVALRY_CHARIOT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>It is important to remember, that for much of antiquity most people lived outside of states. While Mesopotamia hosted Babylon, Assyria and Sumer, and while the Shang Dynasty formed in ancient China, vast numbers of people lived outside of these realms. While soon powers based around highly mobile horse archers would emerge – powers like the Parthians who menaced Central Asia around 250 BCE – the first such mobile, raiding technology was the chariot, and for the origins of that we must go thousands of years prior. Early chariots first appear in central Asian archaeological sites amongst people such as the Sintashta or Maykop. Following upon the domestication of horses also in this region, the spoked wheel allowed people to move themselves – and war parties – across the open plain (although such technologies became less useful in monsoon-prone areas, forested regions, or broken terrain.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_CAVALRY_CHARIOT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Chariots were vital to the movement of early peoples. When the Egyptians were overtaken by the raiding Hyksos in around 1600 BCE, their attackers came on the backs of chariots. For the Vedic people of India – similar migrants attached to and following their horses – the chariot becomes a central part of their imagery (as in its significance in the Rig Veda). The Chinese Shang Dynasty themselves used chariots as supply trains, but were in turn challenged by raiding outsiders who had adapted these for war.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_CAVALRY_CHARIOT_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Over time, new technologies emerged. In the Near East, groups such as the Parthians adopted the composite bow, allowing a horse and rider to move (and strike) much more quickly than a charioteer. In China, a combination of new crossbow technology, better anti-cavalry weapons, and the adoption of mounted composite bow archery led to the chariot’s decline, although chariots remained in use as fancy wagons for centuries onwards.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Clan Type: Naval-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_NAVAL_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_1">
			<Text>The Seafaring clan is a type of Clan present when Barbarian Clans mode is active.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_NAVAL_CHAPTER_CONTENT_PARA_2">
			<Text>Seafaring clans always place their Outposts on coastal plots. They defend their Outposts with land-based anti-cavalry units, but otherwise they exclusively use naval melee and naval ranged units for scouting and attacking.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_NAVAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_TITLE">
			<Text>History</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_NAVAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>A loosely-organized band of nomadic or raiding peoples that make their lives off of the sea, and occasionally plunder – these are pirates! The word "pirate kingdom" might conjure images of peglegs and parrots, modern-day movies and musicals, but in history pirate kingdoms (or republics) formed in lawless places on the fringes of empire, especially near lucrative trade routes, and where complicated island systems meant that those who knew the local sea well could easily hide. The Republic of Pirates, perhaps the most readily recognizable of these, was a brief-lived confederacy of pirates based in what is now the Bahamas, with pirates as famous as Mary Read, Anne Bonny, Calico Jack as well as Blackbeard himself.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_NAVAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>But, significantly, the governor of the pirate capital at New Providence declared that he would make it a "new Madagascar." In other words, pirate states were a known, and common, and worldwide phenomenon. In Southeast Asia from the 1400s – 1800s, various lesser sultanates (especially the Sultanate of Sulu) made a living raiding shipping lanes moving through the area around eastern Indonesia and the Philippines. In the 1200-1500s, the coasts of East Asia were plagued by "Wokou," a word that means "Japanese pirates," but really referred to a multi-ethnic band of sea raiders based in the waters between Korea, China and Japan. And, of course, in east Africa, Madagascar and the Somali coast have been infamous for pirate activity – and are still.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_CLANTYPE_NAVAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Piracy, like many other raiding societies, requires trade. Especially in the era of European trading companies (1500s-1700s) or the sending of tribute to Ming China (1300s–1600s), profitable ships laden with treasure were moving vast distances across unguarded parts of the ocean, and the temptation to grab that treasure has appealed to people of nearly every continent.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</GameData>
