<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<GameData>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- civs -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_CIVINFO_VIETNAM_LOCATION">
			<Text>Southeast Asia</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_CIVINFO_VIETNAM_SIZE">
			<Text>331,210 square km (205,804 square mi)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_CIVINFO_VIETNAM_POPULATION">
			<Text>98,721,275 (in 2020)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_CIVINFO_VIETNAM_CAPITAL">
			<Text>Hanoi (Hà Nội)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VIETNAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Vietnam has one of the oldest historical records in Southeast Asia, a record that reflects a constant struggle for independence and against foreign occupation – against Chinese emperors, European colonialists, and even the United States.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VIETNAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The early Vietnamese - "Kinh" - settled in the Red River delta and began cultivating the land with irrigated rice patties as early as 1200 BCE during the Hồng Bàng dynasty. According to legend, Lạc Long Quân taught the early Vietnamese farmers how to cultivate rice, and by the sixth century BCE, they’d harnessed the waterways around them and built irrigation systems, canals and dikes. Grain cultivation brings people together, and urbanization means the development of artisans and crafts. In Vietnam, this meant complex silks, copper, and bronze tools and weapons. Especially impressive during this time are the Đông Sơn bronze drums.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VIETNAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>But where there is prosperity, there is war. Vietnam has had since its beginning a complicated history with its northern neighbor - the various Chinese dynasties. Vietnamese people incorporated East Asian Confucianism and Mahayana Buddhism (as opposed to the Theravada Buddhism of neighboring Laos and Cambodia), Chinese characters, Chinese concepts of land rulership, and – to the gratitude of historians – Chinese traditions of record-keeping. But this was all not just cultural exchange. Armies got involved.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VIETNAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Triệu Đà, or Zhao Tuo, was a Chinese general who conquered Northern Vietnam, but after the Chinese Qin Dynasty itself fell apart, he decided that he could become an Emperor himself. He founded the Nanyue or Nam Việt kingdom in territories that are now southern China and northern Vietnam. This raises the question: was Triệu Đà a Vietnamese emperor or a Chinese one? This is a good question – and a tremendously politically-loaded one. However, it is one for historians to solve, as Zhao Tuo's imperial ambitions came crashing down when the Han Dynasty defeated Nanyue and incorporated Vietnam into China. Whatever Triệu Đà had been, he wasn't it any more.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VIETNAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>This was to be the first – but certainly not the last – period where the Vietnamese resisted an occupation. Chinese laws, especially ones that limited the power of women, chafed the Vietnamese, who had long incorporated the more matriarchal traditions of Southeast Asia. So it is unsurprising that women were the ones to rise up. In 40 CE, the Trưng Sisters stood up to the Han governor Su Dung. They led a successful revolt, taking sixty-five states in the name of an independent Vietnamese state. The eldest sister, Trưng Trắc, was crowned queen and the sisters maintained their power for two years before Emperor Guangwu finally had enough. He sent an army to recapture the lands and to take the sisters' heads. He never got those: following their defeat, the sisters committed suicide rather than be taken alive and humiliated by the enemy.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VIETNAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>But the rebels persisted. In 225 AD, Triệu Thị Trinh, also known as Lady Triệu,or Bà Triệu, led a new rebellion. Although she was defeated, like the Trưng Sisters, her impact remained. Rebellions continued under leaders like Lý Bôn, although Vietnam was not to be independent until 938 CE. But in that first millennium CE, even under occupation, Vietnam flourished, and archaeologists have discovered trade goods extending all the way to Rome in Vietnamese sites.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VIETNAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>After the decisive Battle of Bạch Đằng in 938 CE, Vietnam was independent, but unstable. The country seethed with civil war for nearly twenty years until Đinh Bộ Lĩnh founded the Đinh dynasty. Under the Đinh, the country was renamed to Đại Cồ Việt, or "Great Viet Land." Đinh established strict laws and worked to form alliances with prominent families, but his rule would only last for eight years before both he and the crown prince were assassinated. Song dynasty China, watching the drama unfold, decided to take advantage of the situation and invaded. Rather than the assassinated king’s six-year-old son taking the throne, Lê Đại Hành married the boy’s mother and took over, thus beginning the Early Lê dynasty. He defeated the Chinese attack via clever tactics (which Chinese records do not specify, but which led to the execution of all of the commanders and generals involved in the loss). After that, China gave the region up (for the time being), but this was probably thanks to the arrangement of tribute that Vietnam paid them than out of real fear. Why go through the trouble of occupying when you're getting regular paychecks?</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VIETNAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Vietnam would remain independent for nearly five hundred years. Vietnam spread, too, down the coast from the Red River valley (Hanoi region) towards the Mekong Delta. This involved a series of wars against and conquests of other ethnic groups, including the Cham and the Khmer (Cambodians); indeed, in the Mekong Delta there are many ethnic Khmer, practicing their own version of Buddhism and speaking Cambodian today.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VIETNAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>The Lý dynasty that followed the expansion southward laid the groundwork for Vietnam as it is today. It was a prosperous period that lasted four hundred years and involved a focus inward. The Lý wanted their economy to thrive, and to do that, they started by investing in their population – establishing, for instance, the Quốc Tử Giám, or “the Temple of Literature.” Education wasn’t limited to nobility, and, in a Confucian meritocratic system that would be recognizable from Vietnam to China to Korea to Japan, commoners could take exams to try to rise to positions within the government.  This wasn't just a male-dominated system, either: the tax system was reorganized with women in charge of the collection. Religion took on a greater role in society during the Lý dynasty, particularly Buddhism, Confucianism, and Taoism.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VIETNAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>This period was not without conflict, however. As the Lý dynasty gave way to the Trần dynasty, Vietnam faced both Mongol and (more) Chinese invasions, as well as a rebellion by the formerly conquered Cham people. These wars, coupled with the declining reputation of the Trần rulers, left Vietnam’s defenses open to betrayal. In the 1400s, General Hồ Quý Ly seized the throne and declared a set of bold and progressive reforms that weren’t popular with the feudal landlords. These nobles went to China’s Ming dynasty for help in restoring the Trần dynasty, and China once again took over Vietnam in 1407. Under Chinese law, Vietnam was once again pressured to adopt a more Chinese culture, and like before, Vietnam resisted. A wealthy farmer named Lê Lợi led the rebellion, ultimately succeeding and starting the new Lê dynasty (later succeeded by Tây Sơn and Nguyễn – this latter dynasty’s name was so popular that thousands of families changed their names to Nguyễn: now by far the most common Vietnamese last name!). The Lê dynasty was influenced by Confucian ideologies, which led to the introduction of new, more progressive laws. Education and expansion once more took precedence.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VIETNAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_11">
			<Text>So, when Europeans began to appear in the 1700s, their efforts to spread Christianity was seen by many as a direct assault on the foundations of Vietnamese civilization. And, in a sense, they were not wrong - religion was indeed the pretext for Vietnam's colonial occupation. Because of the execution of French missionaries, the French (with Spanish allies) invaded southern Vietnam, took it, and held it. French advances persisted, and by 1887, France controlled all of Vietnam, Cambodia, and Laos.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VIETNAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_12">
			<Text>French Indochina seemed to be constantly at war. France fought with Siam over claims to Laos, and when they weren’t fighting Siam, they were fighting Vietnamese rebels. And, just after the latest round of rebellions stopped, World War II began.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VIETNAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_13">
			<Text>Here enters another figure on to the Vietnamese scene: Hồ Chí Minh. Hồ was educated in France, lived an early life working manual labor in the US and UK, and was an astute scholar of politics. Hồ began to sympathize with revolutionaries of all stripes: French, American, and Russian, and, in World War II, returned to Vietnam to fight against the occupying Japanese and Vichy French forces. After the war, Hồ read the Vietnamese Declaration of Independence, which begins with the oddly familiar line, “All people are created equal; they are endowed by their Creator with certain inalienable Rights; among these are Life, Liberty, and the pursuit of Happiness”. Indeed, Hồ, who had been assisted in his fights against the Axis powers in World War II by the Americans, briefly thought that the USA would support Vietnamese independence from France. In this, he was incorrect, and US support for French colonial occupation pushed Hồ’s Việt Minh movement, based in Hanoi, closer and closer to the Soviet Union. Vietnamese forces eventually defeated the French in the battle of Diên Biên Phu and ending the French occupation in 1954. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_VIETNAM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_14">
			<Text> But Vietnam at the end of the war was split between the Soviet-backed North and the US-backed South. This split moved into open war almost immediately after independence, leading to an exchange called by the US the Vietnam War and by the Vietnamese, the American War. Hồ and the northern Vietnamese forces were victorious in this, and he established the Socialist Republic of Vietnam, which exists still today. But immediately after the war came another – Vietnam invaded Cambodia in an attempt to oust the murderous Khmer Rouge regime. The Khmer Rouge were Chinese allies, and the war thus prompted (yet another) Chinese invasion in 1979. Somehow, after nearly a century of constant war, the Vietnamese repelled the Chinese forces – yet another act of resistance.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- leaders -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_CHINA_TITLE">
			<Text>Kublai Khan (China)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_CHINA_QUOTE">
			<Text>Enter into friendly relations with each other from now on. We think all countries belong to one family.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_CHINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>If anyone could expand and unite the Mongolian Empire, it would be the grandson of Genghis Khan. Kublai Khan reigned from 1260 to 1294 AD and created an empire that ran from the Korean Peninsula to the very edges of modern-day Baghdad.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_CHINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Kublai was born in 1215 AD and was the fourth son of Tolui. Even as a child, he proved to be a skilled horseman and warrior. He joined his father on campaign and gained a reputation even as a teenager for being a respectable fighter. Kublai also spent time educating himself, especially in Chinese arts and literature, which would help him later as he became the Yuan Emperor.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_CHINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>After his father died, Kublai watched the line of succession. Finally, the title of Great Khan passed to Kublai’s older brother Möngke. Initially, he supported his older brother's rule, and his loyalty earned him the position of ilkhan, or viceroy. He used this time to learn from his brother, make allies, gather his advisors, and serve as a warrior on the field when needed. However, following his brother’s death in 1259, AD, he was forced to fight against his younger brother, Ariq Böke (who was far less patient than Kublai had been), for the title of Great Khan. Despite Ariq Böke’s popularity, Kublai commanded more resources and the support of multiple princes from across Central Asia, giving him the edge needed to secure the title.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_CHINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Being “Great Khan” wasn’t enough, though. Kublai wanted more. Looking at the bigger picture, Kublai saw a split empire—the remnants of his grandfather’s legacy—and he sought to unite it once more, and to take it even further. He set his eyes on China.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_CHINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>The initial foray in to China took five years, but Kublai steadily captured Chinese cities, beginning with Hsiang-yang and Fan-ch’eng before moving on to take the capital of Song, Lin-an, in 1276 AD. He was merciful and spared the Chinese boy-emperor and his mother, keeping the two as political prisoners within his court. In 1278, Kublai achieved his goal of being declared Emperor after defeating the final prince that stood in his way via a decisive naval battle. With his victory, he became the first Mongol to rule all of China. He started the Yuan Dynasty, and served as its first ruler.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_CHINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Kublai strategically styled himself in the traditional garb of Chinese emperors. Rather than forcing himself and Mongolian ways on his new subjects, he slipped them in like a splinter—noticeable, but not that much of a pain. Kublai made sure, of course, that Mongolians maintained power, especially within the higher brackets of government, but he didn’t repress his new subjects. Merchants, artisans, central Asians, and Mongolian aristocracy ranked high within the new empire. The Han Chinese were relegated to middle and lower-class citizens and were unable to hold state office. Some were allowed to hold administrative positions, however, particularly those who were well-educated. He tolerated other religions and promoted Confucian ideals, and ruled in a manner that was closer to what the Han Chinese were accustomed to than traditional Mongol kingship.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_CHINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Kublai made several economic and class changes during his reign as Emperor. He promoted the use of paper money for transactions and encouraged trade with the West including, surprisingly, accepting Western missionaries, being in direct contact with Pope Gregory X. Kublai also knew Niccolo Polo’s son, Marco. Marco Polo spoke positively about Kublai in his journals, and the two maintained a close relationship for at least seventeen years. Merchants and artisans received a tax break under the new regime in part due to Kublai’s appreciation for the fine porcelain created in China. The economy grew under Kublai’s direction thanks to the Mongols’ ability to control and protect valuable trade routes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_CHINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Although Kublai was generally well-received and seen as a benevolent emperor, not everyone agreed with him or his policies. Han Chinese citizens were less than thrilled with the new class structure and higher taxes that accompanied it. His cousin Kaidu served as a constant threat throughout Kublai’s reign. Kaidu never succeeded, however, in his attempts to unseat the Great Khan and Emperor.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_CHINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Kublai fought to further expand his already vast empire throughout his time as Emperor. Some regions submitted quickly, while others resisted, sometimes, it would seem, with luck more than battle prowess. He tried to invade Japan twice, but both invasions failed because of the Japanese superior naval forces or well-timed storms – the kamikaze, or “divine wind.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_CHINA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>Kublai’s productive reign ended after thirty-four years when he died in 1294. The loss of his (favorite) wife and eldest son drove him into a depression. He had lived to be seventy-nine years old.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_CHINA_CHAPTER_CAPSULE_BODY">
			<Text>Kublai Khan, unlike his grandfather, focuses on establishing [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Routes and using the accompanying [ICON_TechBoosted] Eurekas and [ICON_CivicBoosted] Inspirations to fuel a Science victory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_CHINA_CHAPTER_DETAILED_BODY">
			<Text>With an extra Economic Policy slot available, Kublai Khan is well-positioned for a number of different victories. His [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Routes need to keep running, though, so he should be careful about planning new wars. Kublai is always looking for new friends, as he receives [ICON_TechBoosted] Eurekas and [ICON_CivicBoosted] Inspirations from the first successful [ICON_TradingPost] Trading Post in a foreign Civilization, advances that might assist a Science or Culture Victory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_MONGOLIA_TITLE">
			<Text>Kublai Khan (Mongolia)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_MONGOLIA_CHAPTER_CAPSULE_BODY">
			<Text>Kublai Khan, unlike his grandfather, focuses on establishing [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Routes and using the accompanying [ICON_TechBoosted] Eurekas and [ICON_CivicBoosted] Inspirations to fuel a Science victory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_MONGOLIA_CHAPTER_DETAILED_BODY">
			<Text>With an extra Economic Policy slot available, Kublai Khan is well-positioned for a number of different victories. His [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Routes need to keep running, though, so he should be careful about planning new wars. Kublai is always looking for new friends, as he receives [ICON_TechBoosted] Eurekas and [ICON_CivicBoosted] Inspirations from the first successful [ICON_TradingPost] Trading Post in a foreign Civilization, advances that might assist a Science or Culture Victory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_MONGOLIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>If anyone could expand and unite the Mongolian Empire, it would be the grandson of Genghis Khan. Kublai Khan reigned from 1260 to 1294 AD and created an empire that ran from the Korean Peninsula to the very edges of modern-day Baghdad.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_MONGOLIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Kublai was born in 1215 AD and was the fourth son of Tolui. Even as a child, he proved to be a skilled horseman and warrior. He joined his father on campaign and gained a reputation even as a teenager for being a respectable fighter. Kublai also spent time educating himself, especially in Chinese arts and literature, which would help him later as he became the Yuan Emperor.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_MONGOLIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>After his father died, Kublai watched the line of succession. Finally, the title of Great Khan passed to Kublai’s older brother Möngke. Initially, he supported his older brother's rule, and his loyalty earned him the position of ilkhan, or viceroy. He used this time to learn from his brother, make allies, gather his advisors, and serve as a warrior on the field when needed. However, following his brother’s death in 1259, AD, he was forced to fight against his younger brother, Ariq Böke (who was far less patient than Kublai had been), for the title of Great Khan. Despite Ariq Böke’s popularity, Kublai commanded more resources and the support of multiple princes from across Central Asia, giving him the edge needed to secure the title.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_MONGOLIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Being “Great Khan” wasn’t enough, though. Kublai wanted more. Looking at the bigger picture, Kublai saw a split empire—the remnants of his grandfather’s legacy—and he sought to unite it once more, and to take it even further. He set his eyes on China.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_MONGOLIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>The initial foray in to China took five years, but Kublai steadily captured Chinese cities, beginning with Hsiang-yang and Fan-ch’eng before moving on to take the capital of Song, Lin-an, in 1276 AD. He was merciful and spared the Chinese boy-emperor and his mother, keeping the two as political prisoners within his court. In 1278, Kublai achieved his goal of being declared Emperor after defeating the final prince that stood in his way via a decisive naval battle. With his victory, he became the first Mongol to rule all of China. He started the Yuan Dynasty, and served as its first ruler.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_MONGOLIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Kublai strategically styled himself in the traditional garb of Chinese emperors. Rather than forcing himself and Mongolian ways on his new subjects, he slipped them in like a splinter—noticeable, but not that much of a pain. Kublai made sure, of course, that Mongolians maintained power, especially within the higher brackets of government, but he didn’t repress his new subjects. Merchants, artisans, central Asians, and Mongolian aristocracy ranked high within the new empire. The Han Chinese were relegated to middle and lower-class citizens and were unable to hold state office. Some were allowed to hold administrative positions, however, particularly those who were well-educated. He tolerated other religions and promoted Confucian ideals, and ruled in a manner that was closer to what the Han Chinese were accustomed to than traditional Mongol kingship.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_MONGOLIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Kublai made several economic and class changes during his reign as Emperor. He promoted the use of paper money for transactions and encouraged trade with the West including, surprisingly, accepting Western missionaries, being in direct contact with Pope Gregory X. Kublai also knew Niccolo Polo’s son, Marco. Marco Polo spoke positively about Kublai in his journals, and the two maintained a close relationship for at least seventeen years. Merchants and artisans received a tax break under the new regime in part due to Kublai’s appreciation for the fine porcelain created in China. The economy grew under Kublai’s direction thanks to the Mongols’ ability to control and protect valuable trade routes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_MONGOLIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Although Kublai was generally well-received and seen as a benevolent emperor, not everyone agreed with him or his policies. Han Chinese citizens were less than thrilled with the new class structure and higher taxes that accompanied it. His cousin Kaidu served as a constant threat throughout Kublai’s reign. Kaidu never succeeded, however, in his attempts to unseat the Great Khan and Emperor.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_MONGOLIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Kublai fought to further expand his already vast empire throughout his time as Emperor. Some regions submitted quickly, while others resisted, sometimes, it would seem, with luck more than battle prowess. He tried to invade Japan twice, but both invasions failed because of the Japanese superior naval forces or well-timed storms – the kamikaze, or “divine wind.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_KUBLAI_KHAN_MONGOLIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_10">
			<Text>Kublai’s productive reign ended after thirty-four years when he died in 1294. The loss of his (favorite) wife and eldest son drove him into a depression, although he lived to be seventy-nine years old.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LADY_TRIEU_TITLE">
			<Text>Bà Triệu</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LADY_TRIEU_QUOTE">
			<Text>I only want to ride the wind and walk the waves, slay the big whales of the eastern sea, clean up frontiers, and save the people from drowning.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LADY_TRIEU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Vietnam has a long history of wars with those who would seek to conquer it. Some of the leaders of these fights are regarded as heroes, or even local divinities. One of the earliest of these was named Triệu.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LADY_TRIEU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In the early 200s AD, northern Vietnam was occupied by the Wu Kingdom – one of three Chinese kingdoms that were struggling for power across the continent. It would have been a tense situation – the Wu already on edge and nervous in their occupation of what they considered a “barbarian south,” and the Vietnamese constantly agitating for independence. The Chinese might well have remembered the experience of the Han Dynasty, and the uprising of the Trưng Sisters over a century before – the Vietnamese certainly did. And in this environment, in a province then called Cửu Chân, near present-day Hanoi, came a remarkable woman. Bà Triệu (“Lady Triệu,” also called Triệu Thị Trinh, though her original name is unknown) fought not only the occupying Chinese, but also to her own society’s expectations of her. She reportedly said, “I’d like to ride storms, kill the killer whales in the open sea, drive out the foreign aggressors, reconquer the country, undo the ties of serfdom, and never bend my back to be the concubine of whatever man.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LADY_TRIEU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Her early life was fraught with loss, oppression, and abuse. She was orphaned, and raised by her brother and his wife, who was less than accepting of the extra mouth to feed. Life was difficult in Vietnam during that time, but Triệu decided to do something about it.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LADY_TRIEU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>When Triệu turned nineteen, she left her abusive household and murdered her sister-in-law on the way out. She fled to a nearby mountain and began to prepare for war, day and night, for months on end. She was angry: about her past, about the oppression her people faced, about the way women were expected to live at the time, and she sought a way to end these injustices. Word began to spread about a mighty warrior on the mountaintop preparing a rebellion against the Chinese, and warriors flocked to Triệu. These rumors led her brother (who didn’t seem to mind that his wife was dead – perhaps this says something about Triệu’s sister-in-law…) up the mountain, where he begged her to give up her fight. Triệu wouldn’t be dissuaded, and she ultimately convinced her brother to join her and her thousand-warrior army.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LADY_TRIEU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>In 248, Bà Triệu struck. She fought in over thirty battles, using guerilla tactics against an asymmetrically powerful occupying force – a theme that was to recur in Vietnamese history. The Chinese at first underestimated her because she was a woman, but as time went on, she became a near-mythic, terrifying figure. Rumor had it she was over nine feet tall and rode into battle on an elephant, crying out with a voice like a temple bell. She wore bright golden armor or, on other occasions, a golden robe (concealing, according to one account, yard-long breasts that she threw over her shoulders while riding) and carried a sword in each hand. Most frightening of all was her beauty and fiery temper. Her prowess on the field and uniform earned her the title “The Lady General Clad in Golden Robe.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LADY_TRIEU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>Lu Yin, the military general charged with putting down Triệu’s uprising, was getting tired of being humiliated by not only a young opponent, but also a female one. The Wu Dynasty escalated the conflict, pouring more and more troops into Vietnam, until eventually Triệu’s homegrown resistance could not keep up. Her armies dwindled, and after months of heavy fighting, she was ultimately defeated. However, rather than allowing herself to be taken by her enemy, she chose her own death and allegedly drowned herself in a river. She was only in her early twenties when she died.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LADY_TRIEU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Later Vietnamese emperors honored Bà Triệu not only as a national hero, but as a goddess.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LADY_TRIEU_CHAPTER_CAPSULE_BODY">
			<Text>Bà Triệu uses her units' movement bonuses and cheaper Thành districts for an effective defense as she acquires [ICON_Culture] Culture – or as a base from which to launch a Domination victory.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_LADY_TRIEU_CHAPTER_DETAILED_BODY">
			<Text>Vietnam is a tough Civilization to conquer. Where other Civilizations' units get bogged down in difficult terrain, Bà Triệu’s military units gain additional movement and defense while in Marshes, Woods, or Rainforest, giving her a clear advantage when fighting in such regions. Additionally, she can build Thành districts without the typical population requirements, providing an extra layer of defense to her homeland and providing additional [ICON_Culture] Culture. While Bà Triệu’s specialty Districts – not including the Thành, which, unlinke the Encampment is not a specialty District - are limited to Woods, Rainforest, or Marshes, her Builders can plant forests earlier, freeing new tiles for new Districts. Vietnam is a highly effective defensive Civilization, well-poised to seek military or cultural victories.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- buildings and districts -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_THANH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The word “thành” refers to a citadel or fort, but classical Vietnamese architecture combined military protection with architectural artistry. The oldest thành in Vietnam is the Thành Cổ Loa, in a district of what is now Hà Nội. Local legend tells of how the king had angered a magical turtle by continually trying to build a thành on the turtle’s back. After becoming aware of this magical, talking, and very very angry turtle, the king agreed to relocate the site for the thành. In thanks, the turtle gave the king a magical crossbow, some thousand times the strength of an ordinary one. While the crossbow has been lost to time, the citadel still stands, with its spiral outer walls and rectangular internal keep.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_THANH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Thành often had a rectangular internal keep surrounded by a moat. The citadel’s walls could be thick and durable, but, at least in the case of the stunning thành at Huế, the upper level was often beautifully painted and carved with dragons and other auspicious symbols of royalty.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_THANH_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>In central Hà Nội, the thành Thăng Long remains the city’s predominant symbol, with its squat central tower and thick walls. Built in 1010, this central fortress was so impressive that it was used as a base by groups as disparate as the royal family, the French military during the colonial period, the Japanese imperial army (as a prison), and the communist People’s Army of Vietnam. It was not just a military outpost, though, as it was decorated with carved stone dragons, elaborate palaces (now destroyed), and, now, serves as a museum.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_DISTRICTS_PAGE_DISTRICT_PRESERVE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In 1862, American writer Henry David Thoreau, wrote that “in wildness is the preservation of the world.” Thoreau was, of course, writing from a particular cultural and historical background, pushing for a Romantic view of nature as something restorative to the human spirit, but something of his statement has rung true for civilizations in many times and places. Civilizations, even as they alter or sometimes flat-out destroy the natural world, seek to preserve something of what they have lost, perhaps seeing that there remains something outside of their grasp. Shinto shrines in Japan keep preserved groves of trees, waterfalls, or even herds of deer in honor of nature spirits. Medieval and early modern European palaces had hunting preserves for the nobility, places often now converted into public parks for the rest and rejuvenation of the masses. These are not exactly wild spaces as Thoreau might have it, but rather wildness cultivated and pruned, made to serve the purposes of the city for beauty, relaxation, hunting, sport, reflection, meditation, or simply a bit of fresh air.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_GROVE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Semi-wild groves figure deeply into the religious and imaginative worlds of many peoples. The 11th-century German chronicler Adam of Bremen describes the grove in Uppsala, present-day Sweden, where human sacrifices to Odin, Thor, and Frey were hanged. Baltic and Celtic peoples likewise held stands of old trees – especially, for the latter, oak – to be holy. In the city of Kyoto, the bamboo grove at Arashiyama remains one of the most peaceful and sacred sites in a city known for its shrines. But perhaps the most famous of groves is Lumbini, the forest garden where the Buddha was born. A grove of ancient trees, preserved and tended, lends a living sacred and cultural heart to a preserve.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_SANCTUARY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>In the Industrial age and later, the notion of preserving natural land for the amusement of nobility or the reflection of priests often gave way to the needs of empire. The British Empire set up twin botanical research facilities: Kew Gardens, opened in its present form in 1840, and a site in Singapore in 1859. These were not only places for the public to stroll, but also centers for scientific research, where new strains of crops could be developed for use across the Empire. Hunting lodges like Berlin’s Grunewald were transformed into public parks for workers in Berlin’s factories, and temple sanctuaries became places in which all – not just priests and monks – could meditate. Here, too, ecologists could have a window onto the natural world that was (and is) in a state of rapid decline. “Sanctuary,” here, has a double meaning – both the preservation of the “wild” for science, art and religion, as well as a place of refuge from the demands of the punch-clock, factory whistle, or smartphone.</Text>
		</Row>
	<!-- units -->
	<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_VIETNAMESE_VOI_CHIEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
	<Text>In Southeast Asian civilizations from Burma to Siam to Cambodia, the elephant is the quintessential symbol of royal power. A Southeast Asian knight astride a war elephant and wielding a long spear would have been a formidable foe, and an elephant with a crossbow on its back could be a deadly and mobile siege weapon. Even with the advent of gunpowder, the high perch that an elephant’s back afforded would give a sharpshooter an impressive tactical advantage. In Vietnam, war elephants - voi chiến – were used to stop the Mongol advance in the 13th century. But the elephant was important in Vietnam long before that, both as a weapon as well as a symbol of power. The Trưng sisters in the first century AD rode elephants into battle in their war of rebellion against the Chinese Han dynasty. Later, Bà Triệu, in yet another conflict with China, is also depicted astride a war elephant.</Text>
	</Row>
	<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_VIETNAMESE_VOI_CHIEN_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
	<Text>While elephants could resist musket fire, cannons were another story. By the twentieth century, war elephants fell largely out of use, although the Vietnamese still used them to move supplies and troops quickly and quietly through the jungle during wars against the French, United States, and China. Such support elephants are still used today by Kachin rebel groups in Myanmar (former Burma).</Text>
	</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</GameData>
