<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<GameData>
	<EnglishText>
		<!--Search Terms-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_TERM_INDUSTRY">
			<Text>Industry</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_TERM_INDUSTRIES">
			<Text>Industries</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_TERM_CORPORATION">
			<Text>Corporation</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_TERM_CORPORATIONS">
			<Text>Corporations</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_TERM_MONOPOLY">
			<Text>Monopoly</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_TERM_MONOPOLIES">
			<Text>Monopolies</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_TERM_PRODUCT">
			<Text>Product</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_TERM_PRODUCTS">
			<Text>Products</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- Game Mode Concept -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MONOPOLIES_CHAPTER_CONTENT_TITLE">
			<Text>Industries, Monopolies &amp; Corporations</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MONOPOLIES_CHAPTER_WELCOME_TITLE">
			<Text>Welcome</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MONOPOLIES_CHAPTER_WELCOME_PARA_1">
			<Text>You enjoy your luxuries, but maybe it’s time to mobilize them for profit. The Monopolies and Corporations mode enables you to build Industries around Luxury resources, which give particular bonuses depending on the resource, found Corporations to improve those yields, manufacture unique Products – brands that act as economic Great Works, and, finally, secure a Monopoly. This Mode is one that is significant in all time periods, but really gets going in the later game.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MONOPOLIES_CHAPTER_INDUSTRIES_TITLE">
			<Text>Establishing Industries</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MONOPOLIES_CHAPTER_INDUSTRIES_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once a civilization has improved two of the same type of Luxury resource and has completed the Currency technology they have the opportunity to establish an Industry around that resource. Resources owned by city-states also count toward this requirement if the player is suzerain of the city-state. This is done by using a Builder’s charge on top of an existing Improvement on any one of the Luxury resources. Only one Industry is allowed in a city at a time.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MONOPOLIES_CHAPTER_INDUSTRIES_PARA_2">
			<Text>In addition to providing Great Merchant points, Industries grant particular bonuses to their city based on the type of resource they improve:[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Amber: +25% [ICON_Faith] Faith yield.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Citrus: +30% [ICON_Production] Production toward military units.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Cocoa: +20% Growth and +3 [ICON_Housing] Housing.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Coffee: +20% [ICON_Culture] Culture yield.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Cotton: +30% [ICON_Production] Production toward military units.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Diamonds: +25% [ICON_Gold] Gold yield.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Dyes: +25% [ICON_Faith] Faith yield.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Furs: +30% [ICON_Production] Production toward civilian units.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Gypsum: +30% [ICON_Production] Production toward buildings.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Honey: +20% Growth and +3 [ICON_Housing] Housing.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Incense: +25% [ICON_Faith] Faith yield.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Ivory: +30% [ICON_Production] Production toward military units.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Jade: +25% [ICON_Gold] Gold yield.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Marble: +30% [ICON_Production] Production toward buildings.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Mercury: +15% [ICON_Science] Science yield.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Olives: +30% [ICON_Production] Production toward civilian units.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Pearls: +25% [ICON_Faith] Faith yield.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Salt: +20% Growth and +3 [ICON_Housing] Housing.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Silk: +20% [ICON_Culture] Culture yield.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Silver: +25% [ICON_Gold] Gold yield.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Spices: +20% [ICON_Culture] Culture yield.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Sugar: +20% Growth and +3 [ICON_Housing] Housing.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Tea: +15% [ICON_Science] Science yield.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Tobacco: +30% [ICON_Production] Production toward military units.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Truffles: +25% [ICON_Gold] Gold yield.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Turtles: +15% [ICON_Science] Science yield.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Whales: +30% [ICON_Production] Production toward military units.[NEWLINE][ICON_BULLET] Wine: +20% [ICON_Culture] Culture yield.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MONOPOLIES_CHAPTER_CORPORATIONS_TITLE">
			<Text>Founding Corporations</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MONOPOLIES_CHAPTER_CORPORATIONS_PARA_1">
			<Text>After researching Economics, and after securing at least three instances of the same Luxury resource and establishing an Industry, it’s time to found a Corporation. These require a Great Merchant instead of a Builder to create, and the Great Merchant is retired once the Corporation is created. Corporations can only be built on top of Industry improvements. Corporations grant double the Industry bonus for the appropriate resource to their home city. You can name your Corporation whatever you like, or use the automated name generator!</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MONOPOLIES_CHAPTER_CORPORATIONS_PARA_2">
			<Text>There can only be one Corporation for each Luxury resource in the world, but Corporations can be put 'out of business' if an opposing player manages to control more instances of the resource than the owning player. Once an opponent secures a controlling interest in another Corporation's resource, they can form their own Corporation around it, and the original owner's Corporation is removed.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MONOPOLIES_CHAPTER_PRODUCTS_TITLE">
			<Text>Creating Products</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MONOPOLIES_CHAPTER_PRODUCTS_PARA_1">
			<Text>Once you’ve established a Corporation around a specific luxury resource, you can make a unique Product – a brand. These are similar to Great Works, but instead of being housed in museums, they are stored in new Great Work slots in Stock Exchange or Seaport buildings. Once placed, Products provide the benefits of an Industry, giving whatever bonus their original Luxury resource provided to their new city. You can move your Product to any city you like with the appropriate Great Work slot.</Text>
		</Row>    
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MONOPOLIES_CHAPTER_MONOPOLIES_TITLE">
			<Text>Securing Monopolies</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CONCEPTS_PAGE_MONOPOLIES_CHAPTER_MONOPOLIES_PARA_1">
			<Text>Capitalism might thrive on free trade, but savvy merchants know how to squeeze out their competitors. Controlling 60% or more of the world instances of a Luxury resource grants you a Monopoly on that Luxury. Each monopoly gives [ICON_Tourism] Tourism to the owning player, based on the number of resources controlled, multiplied by the number of foreign civilizations that do not control an instance of the monopolized resource. Monopolies also provide a [ICON_Gold] Gold yield per turn, beginning at +5 for controlling the bare minimum but rising to +10 at 75%, and +25 for controlling all instances. Additional +5 [ICON_GOld] Gold per turn is awarded for each major civilization the Monopoly holder is currently trading with. Once you research Mercantilism, you will be able to see the total number of Luxury resources in the world, as well as what percentage each player currently controls. You can control multiple Monopolies, but that seems a little cruel, doesn’t it?</Text>
		</Row>
		<!--Improvements-->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_INDUSTRY_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The term “industry” often calls to mind the Industrial Revolution, with factories filled with steam, and dangerous, whirring machines. But long before the growth of what William Blake called “dark satanic mills”, rulers saw the advantage in bringing people together to intensify their labor. In Classical antiquity as well as beyond, those working in such industries were often those without their own property – most significantly serfs or enslaved peoples (though the workshops surrounding the Egyptian pyramids, contrary to the popular narrative, were worked by wage laborers). As feudalism gave way to the guild system, and then to early modern capitalism, private individuals gained enough money and status to open their own industries, and the stage was set for the history of economics to begin.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_CORPORATION_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Edward, Lord Thurlow, is popularly quoted as saying, “Corporations have neither bodies to be punished, nor souls to be condemned, they therefore do as they like.” The modern-day corporation traces its lineage back to the great trading companies of the 16th-19th century. Facing the uncertainty of transcontinental oceanic trade, something greater needed to be made to outlast the possible death of both ship and owner. The trading companies reshaped the world – goods flowed around the world, but in the end, these companies were also victims of their own riches; global instability rose (in part owing to the action of the trading companies) making trade routes riskier, costs rose along with corruption and mismanagement, and eventually their home empires took over and colonialism moved to a more direct and invasive form. But the model of the corporation, and its utility in creating an artificial, imaginary, legal body that separates individuals from potential risk - and liability - remains with us.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</GameData>
