<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<GameData>
	<EnglishText>
		<!-- civs -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_CIVINFO_PORTUGAL_LOCATION">
			<Text>Southwestern Europe</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_CIVINFO_PORTUGAL_SIZE">
			<Text>92,090 square km (57,222 square mi)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_CIVINFO_PORTUGAL_POPULATION">
			<Text>10,302,674 (in 2020)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_CIVINFO_PORTUGAL_CAPITAL">
			<Text>Lisbon (Lisboa)</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PORTUGAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Portugal went from being a small medieval kingdom on the Atlantic coast of the Iberian peninsula to a massive maritime empire. At its height in the 1500s, Portugal controlled parts of South America, Africa, Asia, and Oceania. As one of the first European countries to take up colonial ventures, Portugal is responsible for the first great wave of globalization: the movement of people, ideas, and spices around the world to an extent never seen before.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PORTUGAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>Like most of Europe, the region that would one day become Portugal was rocked by regional disputes and conquests. Originally a part of Roman Lusitania, Portugal after the Roman Empire became a part of the Al-Andalus region of the Umayyad Caliphate. But don't let the word "conquest" paint too dark a picture: life in Al-Andalus during the turn of the first millennium would have been a bright spot in comparison with many parts of Western Europe, as, while Europe was going through the Dark Ages, arts and learning flourished across the peninsula via centers such as Cordoba.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PORTUGAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Umayyad rule extended until the 1100s, when Dom Afonso Henriques led a successful rebellion. For this, Afonso I is giving the title “The Founder,” in recognition of having established the first independent Portuguese state. Afonso, along with other Christian kings in the region, continued the Reconquista - the campaign to overthrow Moorish (Muslim) rule in Iberia. Famously, Alfonso took Lisbon in 1147, aided (unintentionally) by an influx of English Crusaders taking shelter in Portugal to avoid the stormy Atlantic. Realizing that they could fight their version of the Crusades closer to home, they stayed and helped to expel the Umayyads from the region (they were permitted to loot captured cities and ransom prisoners as payment). In 1249, Afonso III captured the southern city of Faro, solidifying Portuguese dominance within the region. By the 13th century, Portugal’s borders were comparable to what they are today, and they’d made an alliance with the English that was to last through centuries.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PORTUGAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>With Portugal’s newfound independence came an age of maritime exploration. The Portuguese now controlled powerful port cities as well as the benefits of Umayyad astronomy and math, allowing them to take advantage of their coastline to travel across the known (and eventually unknown) ocean. These two traits allowed Portugal to embark on a gamble - trade with Asia by braving the dangerous waters rather than rely upon all of the middlemen who made up the Silk Road - many of whom were still smarting from the loss of the Umayyads. With this in mind, João I, with his three sons, Prince Duarte, Prince Pedro, and Prince Henry “the Navigator” kicked off the Age of Discovery - Discovery, of course, for the Portuguese; residents of Malacca, Goa, and Angola might have had another word for it. This conquest was in a sense the next step from the Reconquista - the first real overseas colony for the Portuguese was the conquest of Ceuta, in North Africa, very close to the Portuguese coast. The Portuguese continued to “explore” the seas and set up colonies starting along the coast of Africa and moving all the way to India and East Asia. By the early 1500s, there were series of Portuguese colonies nearly spanning the world, including places such as Angola, Mozambique, Somalia, Goa (in India), Malacca (in present-day Malaysia), Timor, and a trade post in Japan. The institution of these colonies and trade routes made Portugal very powerful and very wealthy within a short amount of time, as Portuguese merchants controlled the import and export of gold, spices, but also the trafficking of enslaved persons, leading to increased riches and an increased thirst for new conquests, new trade goods - and new converts to Catholicism, an emphasis that was to doom Portuguese colonies in many places; Malay sultans and Japanese daimyo didn't mind trade, but conversion threatened to break apart their political order (something of which the more canny Dutch took note).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PORTUGAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>Portugal had a friendly rivalry with their neighbor, Spain, when it came to this exploration. After Christopher Columbus “discovered” America in 1492 and solidified a Spanish claim to that territory, Portugal knew they had to find a way to one-up their neighbor. Portuguese explorers had stumbled upon the coast of Brazil, and, after a bitter dispute with Spain, the Pope had to step in to finally resolve them with the Treaty of Tordesillas, which divided up the New World’s “discoveries” : those east of the line would be Portuguese, and those west would be Spanish. Both sides found this agreeable enough (not that they’d argue with the Pope) and went about their business of conquest, but as European explorers began to fill in the map, it quickly became apparent that Spain had inherited gold-rich Mexico, Peru, and most of North America, whereas Portugal received coastal Brazil. (No one, it seemed, consulted with the indigenous peoples first).</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PORTUGAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>The peace with their neighbor doesn’t last, however, and after a series of unfortunate events in Portugal led to a throne without an heir, Portugal found themselves seated with a Spanish king. Philip II of Spain claimed the throne through his mother’s line and marched on Portugal. After his decisive victories, he was crowned Philip I of Portugal (since he couldn’t be Philip II there, with no prior Philip I). Portugal wouldn’t be independent again until 1640 after the Portuguese Restoration War, and even then, they had to wait another 28 years for Spain to recognize that independence.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PORTUGAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Fortune appeared to follow after that when gold was discovered in Brazil. The new flow of wealth helped to enrich Portugal’s economy and gave them a financial cushion, something sorely needed when a magnitude nine earthquake hit Lisbon in 1755. Sebastião José de Carvalho e Melo, or the Marquis of Pombal for short, survived the destruction and without a pause, went about rebuilding the city. His swift action had the city rebuilt in a year, and in a stroke of brilliance, he had the buildings designed to withstand earthquakes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PORTUGAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_8">
			<Text>Napoleon invaded Portugal as a part of his conquest of Europe in the 1800s, and when he seized Lisbon, the Portuguese capital moved to Brazil, in Rio de Janeiro. Portugal pushed back Napoleon with the help of their English allies – solidifying a bond that had been present since the beginning. But this move was the end of Portugal's Brazilian claim: at the end of the war, Lisbon became the capital once again after Brazil declared its independence from Portugal.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_CIVILIZATIONS_PAGE_CIVILIZATION_PORTUGAL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_9">
			<Text>Portugal today remains a strongly Catholic nation, and is a core member of the European Union. It remains famous for its food and drink (including green wine!), melancholic fado music, and cosmopolitan outlook. Portugal and Britain keep close ties, although in peak tourist season the Portuguese might sometimes think twice…</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- leaders -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOAO_III_TITLE">
			<Text>João III</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOAO_III_QUOTE">
			<Text>I am Dom João, by the grace of God, King of Portugal and of Algarves, and of lands overseas, in Africa, lord of Guinea, and lord of the conquest and exploration of, and trade with, Ethiopia, Arabia, Persia, and India.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOAO_III_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>João III, called “the Colonizer” or perhaps more kindly the “Pious,” was King of Portugal and the Algarves from 1521 to 1556. He was the oldest son of King Manuel I and Maria of Aragon. From birth, his family sought to set him on a course toward excellence – he was given scholars who taught him astronomy, astrology, theology, law, and the humanities, and he was given his own house to manage at the age of twelve. With a few years of practical work under his belt, he started helping his father with real royal duties.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOAO_III_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>João was set to marry at sixteen and would have married his first cousin Eleanor of Austria, but his father Manuel stepped in and decided he wanted Eleanor for himself. João was understandably offended, and more than a little upset about the whole ordeal. However, following João’s succession in 1521, he made a strategic marriage to Catherine of Austria, who happened to be the younger sister of his ex-fiancé, Eleanor.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOAO_III_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>Burned in love, he threw himself into his religion. Significantly, João sponsored humanistic approaches to religion such as the Society of Jesus – the Jesuits. Perhaps less nobly, it was under João that the Inquisition finally arrived in Portugal, with predictable results both in suppressing free inquiry (but also ensuring that Portugal would have no Protestant movement). The Inquisition was designed to punish what the church considered to be problematic or blasphemous, including anything related to witchcraft, bigamy (recall João’s contemporary in England, Henry VIII, and his struggles with the church over his complicated love life), literature that went against the church, and sexual deviancy. João (with the Pope’s permission) appointed his brother Cardinal Henry as his Grand Inquisitor and established branches across Portuguese territories. The Inquisition’s influence bled into other parts of Portuguese culture and daily life. These moves earned João the name “the Pious.”</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOAO_III_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_4">
			<Text>Rather than conquest through battle, João often used diplomacy and arranged advantageous marriages. His sister Isabella was married to Charles V, the King of Spain and the Holy Roman Emperor, and he married his daughter Maria Manuela to King Philip II of Spain. His son Prince João Manuel married Joan of Spain and their son went onto become King Sebastian I. The common trend here – Portugal securing an independent but closely-allied place in Iberia – should be clear.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOAO_III_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_5">
			<Text>João found that the Portuguese’s expansive empire was inefficient, fraught with debt and corruption. Initially, he tried to patch the problems by appointing new governors, thinking that better men would yield better results, but the problem was systemic. Also, sometimes the “fired” governors just didn’t leave.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOAO_III_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_6">
			<Text>The real impact of João’s reign was in the expansion of his trade networks. Fortified Portuguese trading camps – feitorias – were established in Mombasa, Mozambique, and other parts of Africa, and Portugal acquired Timor and the Maluku Islands in Southeast Asia, Goa and Sri Lanka in South Asia, and a trade outpost in Nagasaki and Macau in East Asia. Further, Portuguese Brazil was, under João, to become a significant colony. These networks were to move spices, sugar, gold, fragrances, and silk across the world. Less nobly, João also trafficked in enslaved people, prompting the Congolese king Mvemba a Nzinga to write João a scathing letter about the activities of Portuguese slave traders.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOAO_III_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_7">
			<Text>Towards the end of João’s reign, he had trouble naming an heir. Of his nine children (born to Catherine), only two survived past childhood, and both died before their father. The throne was ultimately left to his grandson, Sebastian, upon his death in 1557.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOAO_III_CHAPTER_CAPSULE_BODY">
			<Text>Portugal seeks to explore the map to set the stage for a sea-based trade empire, taking advantage of its advantages in coastal resources and nautical exploration.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_LEADERS_PAGE_LEADER_JOAO_III_CHAPTER_DETAILED_BODY">
			<Text>A successful Portuguese victory will depend upon building vast trade networks and exploiting coastal tiles. Bear in mind that, for Portugal, international [ICON_TradeRoute] Trade Routes are limited to those that pass over water, so João will want to build his cities along the coast to maximize potential trading spots. Further, coastal cities can take full advantage of the Navigation School, giving extra [ICON_Production] Production towards naval units, extra [ICON_Science] Science for coast and lake tiles, and extra [ICON_GreatAdmiral] Great Admiral points. Portugal will want to explore the map early to find future sites for Portugal’s Unique Infrastructure, the Feitoria, built by Portugal’s Unique Unit, the Nau. Portugal can use its trading profits to fuel any kind of win – steer clear of wars, though; those ports need to stay open for business!</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- buildings and districts -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_NAVIGATION_SCHOOL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
		<Text>Sagres is the southernmost point in Portugal, the last safe shelter before ships would depart across the storm-tossed Atlantic. Looking south, Portuguese sailors faced rough seas and the forbidding “Cabo de Não” – “Cape No,” that stretch of the Atlantic coast of what is now Morocco where the Sahara begins. For long considered the end of the navigable world (hence the name) by European and Arab sailors, Cabo de Não (now called Cape Chaunar) had to be overcome for the Portuguese to realize their dream of a ship-based empire.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_BUILDINGS_PAGE_BUILDING_NAVIGATION_SCHOOL_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
		<Text>The planning for – and ultimate success of – Portuguese expeditions around the Cape, and around other, farther, more forbidding capes, happened at schools of navigation. While some scholars interpret this “school” term loosely, noting that most Portuguese sailors probably did their studying practically aboard ships, others posit a centralized school of navigation – placed by the most romantically-inclined scholars right at the Sagres Point. From here, sailors would be able to see firsthand the dangers of the Atlantic… and plot out ways to overcome them.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_ETEMENANKI_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
		<Text>Etemenanki was a Babylonian ziggurat or stepped tower. Some believe that Etemenanki may be the inspiration for the story of the Tower of Babel. It was originally constructed around the time of Hammurabi and restored by Nebuchadnezzar II after the destruction of Babylon in 689 BC. In 331 BC, Alexander the Great captured Babylon and once more ordered for Etemenanki to be repaired. When he returned to Babylon and found that the building hadn’t changed, he decided it would be easier just to knock the whole thing down and start again. Alexander the Great died however before his orders could be fulfilled. Another prince allegedly wanted to rebuild the ziggurat, but after he embarrassed himself by tripping, he had his elephants knock the rest of it down in a temper tantrum.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_TORRE_DE_BELEM_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
		<Text>The Torre de Belém is one of Portugal’s most recognizable structures and serves a monument to the Age of Discovery. The tower stands defensively in Lisbon’s harbor and acted as the starting point for many explorers setting off into the Atlantic. King Manuel I commissioned Francisco de Arruda in the 16th century to design and build the structure. The tower is made from limestone and is designed in the ornate Manueline style. The grand stonework is visible from a distance. If someone were to give the tower a closer look, they would see sculptures and most curiously, a rhinoceros head carved into the stone. Even with its exterior grandeur and beauty, it was functional and served as an active defense for the region.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- improvements -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_FEITORIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>The feitoria – literally “factory” – was a trade depot set up overseas to facilitate trade, and, as such, it was a key institution of early mercantilist projects, especially the Portuguese networks of the early modern period (1300s-1600s). Here, European merchants could exchange goods in a space protected by European arms, operating with some degree of independence from the local ruler – and local pirates. Feitoria had a dark side, however: non-Europeans were not allowed to own land within one, and, later, they were key outposts of European colonization. Worse, the feitorias were key outposts in the trafficking of enslaved people.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_IMPROVEMENTS_PAGE_IMPROVEMENT_FEITORIA_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The first Portuguese feitoria was in the North African country of Mauritania, but later outposts were in Goa (in India), Malacca (in present-day Malaysia), Ternate (present-day Indonesia), Macau (in China), and Nagasaki (in Japan). In each spot, the Portuguese left their mark: Malacca and Goa have sizeable Catholic populations, Macau has impressive architecture left over from the Portuguese period, and bakers in Nagasaki still make Portuguese-style castella (kasutera, in Japanese) cakes.</Text>
		</Row>
		<!-- units -->
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_PORTUGUESE_NAU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>During the 1300s to the 1500s, the Portuguese dominated the seas. Trade networks linked Lisbon and ports across Asia, Africa, and the New World, and reshaped how we see the world today. For instance, without the Portuguese introduction of New World chili peppers to Asia, we would not have spicy Thai food, and without the Portuguese presence in Japan, we would not have tempura (from the Latin quatuor anni tempora – a time of eating no meat). But it was not all spices: nau transported gold, Catholic missionaries… and enslaved persons.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_UNITS_PAGE_UNIT_PORTUGUESE_NAU_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>The nau was a larger version of the caravel, with square sails in the front, and triangular sails on the mizzenmast. Their heavy build allowed them to navigate stormier seas, especially around the southern tips of Africa and South America, and to reach farther than the caravel or cog.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</GameData>
