<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<GameData>
	<EnglishText>
		<Row Tag="LOC_TOWERDEFENSE_ZOMBIE_COMBAT_STRENGTH_DESC">
			<Text>+{Property} Mutation Strength</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_IMPROVEMENT_ANCIENT_TOWER_DEFENSE_NAME">
			<Text>Barricade</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_IMPROVEMENT_MODERN_TOWER_DEFENSE_NAME">
			<Text>Reinforced Barricade</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_IMPROVEMENT_ANCIENT_TRAP_DEFENSE_NAME">
			<Text>Trap</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_IMPROVEMENT_MODERN_TRAP_DEFENSE_NAME">
			<Text>Modernized Trap</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_IMPROVEMENT_ANCIENT_TOWER_DEFENSE_DESC">
			<Text>An unworkable early Improvement that deals minor damage to, and exerts zone of control on, hostile units passing through or adjacent to it. Unlocked with Military Engineering and built using a Builder Charge. Does not prevent unit movement through this space.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_IMPROVEMENT_MODERN_TOWER_DEFENSE_DESC">
			<Text>An unworkable later Improvement that deals moderate damage to, and exerts zone of control on, hostile units passing through or adjacent to it. Unlocked with Rifling and built using a Charge from a Military Engineer. Does not prevent unit movement through this space.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_IMPROVEMENT_ANCIENT_TRAP_DEFENSE_DESC">
			<Text>An unworkable early Improvement that deals moderate damage to, and depletes the movement of, hostile units passing directly through it. Unlocked with Construction and built using a Builder Charge. Does not prevent unit movement through this space.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_IMPROVEMENT_MODERN_TRAP_DEFENSE_DESC">
			<Text>An unworkable later Improvement that deals significant damage to, and depletes the movement of, hostile units passing directly through it. Unlocked with Ballistics and built using a Charge from a Military Engineer. Does not prevent unit movement through this space.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PROJECT_CONVERT_ZOMBIES_RELIGIOUS_NAME">
			<Text>Turn Undead</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PROJECT_CONVERT_ZOMBIES_SCIENCE_NAME">
			<Text>Dark Signal</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PROJECT_CONVERT_ZOMBIES_RELIGIOUS_DESCRIPTION">
			<Text>Upon completion, gain control of the zombies currently in this city's territory.  Control lasts 15 turns.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PROJECT_CONVERT_ZOMBIES_SCIENCE_DESCRIPTION">
			<Text>Upon completion, gain control of the zombies currently in this city's territory.  Control lasts 30 turns.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_UNIT_MODE_ZOMBIE_NAME">
			<Text>Zombie</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_UNIT_MODE_ZOMBIE_DESCRIPTION">
			<Text>A hostile melee unit that has a chance to appear on the map at a location where a unit has died. Its Melee Strength increases with each Zombie that has been eliminated, globally. If a Zombie destroys another unit, a new Zombie unit spawns in that tile the next turn. If a Zombie reduces a city's population, a new Zombie unit will spawn immediately next to the city. Zombies target the closest nearby unit, city, or defensible district.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_UNITCOMMAND_RELEASE_LEVY_DESCRIPTION">
			<Text>Release control of this unit.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_UNITCOMMAND_SPY_SUMMON_ZOMBIES_NAME">
			<Text>Zombie Outbreak</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_UNITCOMMAND_SPY_SUMMON_ZOMBIES_DESCRIPTION">
			<Text>Upon completion, has a chance to spawn a Zombie for each tile worked by this city.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_NOTIFICATION_SPY_SUMMONED_ZOMBIES_SUMMARY">
			<Text>Your agent {1_unitName} in {2_CityName} succeeded in infecting the population, creating a Zombie horde to attack the city.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_NOTIFICATION_SPY_SUMMONED_ZOMBIES_MESSAGE">
			<Text>Success Causing Zombie Outbreak</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_NOTIFICATION_SPY_ENEMY_SUMMONED_ZOMBIES_SUMMARY">
			<Text>An enemy Spy in {1_CityName} succeeded in infecting your population, creating a Zombie horde that now threaten your city.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_NOTIFICATION_SPY_ENEMY_SUMMONED_ZOMBIES_MESSAGE">
			<Text>Enemy Caused Zombie Outbreak</Text>
		</Row>
	  <Row Tag="LOC_DESCRIPTION_ADDENDUM_WEAK_TRAP">
			<Text>Deals minor damage to and depletes the movement of hostile units walking onto this tile.</Text>
		</Row>
	  <Row Tag="LOC_DESCRIPTION_ADDENDUM_TRAP">
			<Text>Deals moderate damage to and depletes the movement of hostile units walking onto this tile.</Text>
		</Row>
	  <Row Tag="LOC_DESCRIPTION_ADDENDUM_BARRICADE">
			<Text>Deals minor damage to and exerts zone of control on hostile units walking onto this tile and those surrounding it.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_IMPROVEMENT_ALCAZAR_DESCRIPTION_ZOMBIE">
			<Text>{LOC_IMPROVEMENT_ALCAZAR_DESCRIPTION}[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]{LOC_DESCRIPTION_ADDENDUM_TRAP}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_IMPROVEMENT_MAORI_PA_DESCRIPTION_ZOMBIE">
			<Text>{LOC_IMPROVEMENT_MAORI_PA_DESCRIPTION}[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]{LOC_DESCRIPTION_ADDENDUM_WEAK_TRAP}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_IMPROVEMENT_ROMAN_FORT_DESCRIPTION_ZOMBIE">
			<Text>{LOC_IMPROVEMENT_ROMAN_FORT_DESCRIPTION}[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]{LOC_DESCRIPTION_ADDENDUM_WEAK_TRAP}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_IMPROVEMENT_FORT_DESCRIPTION_ZOMBIE">
			<Text>{LOC_IMPROVEMENT_FORT_DESCRIPTION}[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]{LOC_DESCRIPTION_ADDENDUM_WEAK_TRAP}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_IMPROVEMENT_VAMPIRE_CASTLE_DESCRIPTION_ZOMBIE">
			<Text>{LOC_IMPROVEMENT_VAMPIRE_CASTLE_DESCRIPTION}[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]{LOC_DESCRIPTION_ADDENDUM_WEAK_TRAP}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_IMPROVEMENT_GREAT_WALL_DESCRIPTION_ZOMBIE">
			<Text>{LOC_IMPROVEMENT_GREAT_WALL_DESCRIPTION}[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]{LOC_DESCRIPTION_ADDENDUM_BARRICADE}</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
</GameData>
